A Guide to the Papers of David Scott Meikleham, 1833-1888 (1954)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of David Scott Meikleham 1833-1888 (1954)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4726-c
This collection consists of 60 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of David Scott Meikleham were loaned to the library by the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1976 August 11.
Scope and Content
Dr. Meikleham's medical papers contain an 1849 autopsy, an undated discussions, both original and copied, of gout, arsenic, smallpox, morphine poisoning, leg amputation, tuberculosis, and yellow fever, as well as letters of recommendation from Glasgow physicians, and scattered correspondence on medical topics including his ulcerated foot, and accusations of overcharging. Family letters include descriptions of sleighing on Broadway, Jefferson and Randolph family genealogy, and photographs of Septimia Ann Randolph Meikleham and an unidentified man.
Contents List
- Copy of David Scott Meikleham's medical degree from the University of Glasgow with receipt for the same from the United States consulate 1833, ADS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:1)
  The copy made and notarized 1841 May 14. The receipt is attached by a wax seal.
- Copies of letters of recommendation written for D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham by Richard Miller, John MacFarlane, W. Auchinshloss, John Burns, William Cooper, Alex Panton, 1833, ALS copy, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:2)
- . Letter of recommendation written for D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham by Dr. William Couper 1833 May 14, ALS, 1 p.; with handwritten copy. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Letter of recommendation written for D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham by Dr. Alex Panton 1833 May 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with handwritten copy. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Letter of recommendation written by D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham by Dr. M Auchinshloss 1837 February 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:5)
- His friends in Havana to D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham 1843 June 30, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Joseph T. Crawford to David Scott Meikleham 1843 July 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:7)
- D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham to Sir Phillip Crampton 1844 April 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:8)
- D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham to subscribers of the New York Medical Intelligence1845 December 17, 3 printed letters. (Box-folder 1:9)
- D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham to Messrs. Goodhue and Company, 1847 July 3 to July 9, 3 ALS copies, 5 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Three copies of letters with and additional "copy of account of the late Mr. DeConinck," originally enclosed in the letter.
- [David Scott Meikleham] to [Messrs. Goodhue and Company], 1847 July 12, AL draft, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Autopsy Report: "Examination of the body of A. Ogden Esq." by D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham 1849 July 30, AMsS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Bottom of page tattered and torn.
- Cribson Shattleru to Randolph Meikleham, 1876 October 12, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Concerning the disposition of Miss Scott's Estate.
- Cribson Shattleru to Miss E. J. Meikleham 1876 October 12, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Cribson Shattleru to Miss E. A. Meikleham, 1876 October 12, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Cribson Shattleru to Randolph Meikleham, 1877 April 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:16)
- Cribson Shattleru to Miss E. J. Meikleham, 1877 April 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
- One receipt from Alice Meikleham to T. U. R. Meikleham 1877 December 15, ADS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:18)
- William Meikleham to Harry [Meikleham] 1888 February 26, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Copied from a statement sent by Miss Meikleham by Landon C. Bell, 1924 May, ANs, 8 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 1:20)
- Landon C. Bell to Mrs. James Morphy including an extract from Bell's The Old Free State1927 September 19, ALS, 10 pp. on 7 l. (Box-folder 1:21)
- Katherine M. Morphy to Capt. Henry P. Meikleham, 1927 September 29, ALS copy, 8 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Letter very brittle, and some cracked folds.
- Albemarle County Circuit Court notice informing heirs to the estate of Thomas J. Randolph that they are being sued for non payment of taxes, 1954 May 1, TD, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 1:23)
- Notes on M. Boudin's discussion of the use of arsenic in the cure of disease taken by [David Scott Meikleham] n.y. August 26, ANs, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:25)
- Description of leg amputation by [David Scott Meikleham] n.y. October 19, Ms, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:25)
- Medical Discussion: Morbid States of Mucous Membranes by [David Scott Meikleham] n.d., AMs, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:26)
- M. Chomel on the treatment of Bariola by [David Scott Meikleham] n.d., ANs, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:27)
- Description of a case of morphine poisoning by [David Scott Meikleham] n.d., Ms, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:28)
- Discussion of the yellow fever symptoms issue by [David Scott Meikleham] n.d., Ms, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:29)
- Medical Report: Examination of the chest by [David Scott Meikleham] n.d., MsS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:30)
- Fourteen receipts for newspaper subscription written for David Scottt Meikleham 1837 to 1838, ADS, 16 pp. on 16 l. (Box-folder 1:31)
  All items glued together.
- Calendar with Randolph family genealogical material written on the back n.d., ANs, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:32)
- Randolph family genealogical materials n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:33)
- Photograph of Septimia Ann Randolph Meikleham and three copies of a photograph of an unidentified person n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:34)
- David Scott Meikleham's personal account of his travels and medical history from 1833 to ca. 1844 n.d., Ms, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:35)